<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-27T08:13:44+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">You Group @ UCSD</title><subtitle>Yi-Zhuang You&apos;s Research Group</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Tale of Two Decays: Why Your AI Assistant Loses “Focus” on Long Tasks</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2025/11/24/LLMFocus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale of Two Decays: Why Your AI Assistant Loses “Focus” on Long Tasks" /><published>2025-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2025/11/24/LLMFocus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2025/11/24/LLMFocus.html"><![CDATA[<p>We’ve all had those moments with ChatGPT or Gemini. One minute, it’s writing a brilliant sonnet, and the next, it fails to multiply two large numbers or loses the plot halfway through a complex logical deduction. It begs the question: <strong>What is actually happening inside the “mind” of an LLM?</strong> Is it a reasoning agent, capable of complex thought? Or is it, as some critics suggest, just a “stochastic parrot”—a mimic that predicts the next word without understanding the whole picture?</p>

<p>In our latest paper, “<em>How Focused Are LLMs? A Quantitative Study via Repetitive Deterministic Prediction Tasks</em>” (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00763" target="_blank">arXiv:2511.00763</a>), our team at <em>EdenCode</em> and <em>Path Integral Technology</em>, together with researchers from <em>Harvard University</em> and <em>UC Davis</em>, decided to stop guessing and start measuring. We took a physicist’s approach to studying Artificial Intelligence, treating the LLM not as a magical black box, but as a complex physical system. Here is what we found.</p>

<h3 id="system-1-vs-system-2-parrot-or-scientist">System 1 vs. System 2: Parrot or Scientist?</h3>

<p>To understand why LLMs fail, we first need to look at human cognition. The Nobel laureate Daniel Kahneman described two distinct modes of thinking:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/LLM-system1or2.png" alt="What is LLM's operating mode? A mimicking parrot or a reasoning agent?" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>System 1 (Intuition)</strong> is fast, automatic, and subconscious—think of a <strong>parrot mimicking speech</strong>, responding instantly based on patterns it has heard before, without pausing to understand the underlying logic.</li>
  <li><strong>System 2 (Reasoning)</strong> is slow, deliberate, and conscious—think of a <strong>scientist solving a complex problem</strong>, who must plan, calculate, and verify each step carefully.</li>
</ul>

<p>Current LLMs are masters of <strong>System 1</strong>. They generate the next word immediately based on statistical likelihood. They don’t naturally “stop and think.” But what happens when we force a System 1 thinker to do a System 2 task—something that requires maintaining a coherent chain of logic over a long sequence?</p>

<h3 id="the-experiment-why-accuracy-matters-in-science">The Experiment: Why “Accuracy” Matters in Science</h3>

<p>Evaluating an AI’s performance is usually tricky. If you ask an LLM to “write a poem about the ocean,” there is no single correct answer. You can’t really calculate an “accuracy rate” for poetry or conversation. However, the game changes when we apply <strong>AI for Science</strong>.</p>

<p>In science and math, problems often admit <strong>unique, correct solutions</strong>. If we ask for the sum of two integers, the result is exact. If we ask for the product of quantum operators, there is no room for “creative interpretation.” This scientific context allows us to define a rigorous metric: <strong>SAR (Sequence Accuracy Rate)</strong>. This measures the probability that the <em>entire</em> output sequence is 100% correct. Using this, we tested models on integer addition, cyclic letter replacement, and quantum physics math.</p>

<h3 id="the-accuracy-cliff-defining-the-effective-focus-range">The “Accuracy Cliff”: Defining the Effective Focus Range</h3>

<p>If an LLM were simply making random, independent mistakes at each step (like rolling a die), its accuracy would drop off steadily following an exponential decay as the task got longer. But that’s not what we found. Instead, we observed a phenomenon we call the <strong>Accuracy Cliff</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/tale-of-two-decays.png" alt="The Mystery of LLM Focus: A Tale of Two Decays" /></p>

<p>The models perform perfectly for a while, and then—suddenly—reliability collapses. It’s not a gentle decline; it’s a crash. This threshold defines the model’s <strong>Effective Focus Range</strong>. Within this range, the model is reliable. Beyond it, it hallucinates. Mathematically, we found the errors follow a <strong>double-exponential decay</strong> law. In plain English? <strong>The errors are contagious.</strong> One small mistake doesn’t just stay isolated; it propagates through the model’s attention mechanism, triggering a cascade of failures.</p>

<h3 id="the-physics-of-losing-focus">The Physics of “Losing Focus”</h3>

<p>As a physicist, this curve looks familiar. It resembles <strong>phase transitions</strong> in magnetic materials (specifically, spin glasses). LLMs are built on the “Attention Mechanism”. Every word attends to every other word. While this allows the model to understand context, it also means that <strong>noise propagates globally</strong>.</p>

<p>Think of it like a room full of people trying to pass a complex message: if they whisper primarily to their neighbors (independent errors), the message degrades gradually. But in an LLM, everyone is shouting at everyone else (all-to-all attention). If one person gets confused, that “noise” spreads to everyone else instantly via the dense connections. This is “internal interference.”</p>

<p>To understand this crash quantitatively, we modeled the LLM using the <strong>Sherrington-Kirkpatrick Spin Glass</strong> model, treating every generated token as a tiny magnet (an “Ising spin”)—pointing “up” if correct and “down” if hallucinating. In this physical system, reliability is a tug-of-war between stability and noise. The force keeping the model on track grows linearly with the sequence length (\(N\)), but the chaotic interference—fueled by the model’s all-to-all Attention Mechanism—explodes much faster, scaling as the square of the length (\(N^2\)). For short tasks, stability wins; but as the task lengthens, the quadratic noise inevitably overpowers the linear stability, triggering a sudden “phase transition.” The “spins” don’t just flip randomly one by one; they flip in a correlated burst, causing the entire reasoning chain to collapse in the catastrophic collective error we observe as the Accuracy Cliff.</p>

<h3 id="the-solution-engineering-fault-tolerance">The Solution: Engineering Fault Tolerance</h3>

<p>So, is there hope for long-context reasoning? Yes. Once we understood the physics of the failure (correlated error accumulation), the engineering solution became clear: <strong>Break the loops.</strong></p>

<p>We applied a <strong>Divide-and-Conquer</strong> strategy. Instead of asking the model to solve a massive problem in one breath, we chop the task into smaller, manageable sub-tasks that fit well within the model’s Effective Focus Range: solve Part A, solve Part B, then combine them. By effectively “resetting” the model’s context between steps, we stop the errors from snowballing. Our data shows that this simple algorithmic change pushes the “Accuracy Cliff” significantly further out, turning a hallucinating model into a reliable reasoning agent.</p>

<h3 id="the-future-ai-needs-error-correction">The Future: AI Needs Error Correction</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/physics-of-LLM.png" alt="Physics of LLMs: From Error Mechanism to Fault-Tolerance" /></p>

<p>In quantum computing, we accept that “qubits are noisy,” so we build <strong>Quantum Error Correction</strong> to make them reliable. Our takeaway message is that <strong>Classical AI needs error correction too</strong>. We cannot just build bigger models and hope they magically become perfectly logical. We need to design architectures that acknowledge the intrinsic noise, manage the interference, and engineer fault tolerance into the system. If we want AI that can reason like a scientist (System 2) rather than just mimic like a parrot (System 1), we have to treat it like a complex physical system—and fix the physics.</p>

<p>(<em>Written by Google Gemini 3</em>)</p>

<hr />

<p><em>You can read our full paper on <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00763" target="_blank">arXiv:2511.00763</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Gemini 3</name></author><category term="Machine Learning" /><category term="LLM" /><category term="AI" /><category term="Physics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’ve all had those moments with ChatGPT or Gemini. One minute, it’s writing a brilliant sonnet, and the next, it fails to multiply two large numbers or loses the plot halfway through a complex logical deduction. It begs the question: What is actually happening inside the “mind” of an LLM? Is it a reasoning agent, capable of complex thought? Or is it, as some critics suggest, just a “stochastic parrot”—a mimic that predicts the next word without understanding the whole picture?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can GPT Speak the Quantum Language?</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2024/11/07/ShadowGPT.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can GPT Speak the Quantum Language?" /><published>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2024/11/07/ShadowGPT</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2024/11/07/ShadowGPT.html"><![CDATA[<p>In recent years, we’ve grown accustomed to chatting with AI models like GPT, capable of understanding and generating human language with impressive fluency. But what if we could teach GPT to “speak” the quantum language? Our nature, at its fundamental level, is governed by quantum physics. When we probe quantum systems through measurements, we receive responses in the form of measurement outcomes—the messages from nature about its quantum behavior. These are the <em>quantum language</em> that nature speaks to us. Can we teach AI to understand this quantum language, i.e., training it to predict the outcomes of quantum experiments as if it were a quantum system itself?</p>

<p>In our recent work, we propose an innovative approach: <strong>ShadowGPT</strong> (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03285" target="_blank">arXiv:2411.03285</a>), which enables a GPT language model to generate <em>classical shadows</em>—a specific kind of quantum language that nature used to talk about the quantum world through random measurements. This innovative combination of AI and quantum physics unlocks new ways of understanding complex quantum systems.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/shadowGPT.png" alt="Illustration of ShadowGPT approach" /></p>

<p>Our research centers on a longstanding problem in physics—solving quantum many-body problems. Given a quantum system’s parameters, we want to predict its ground state properties, which tell us how it behaves in its lowest energy state. This challenge is not just a mathematical puzzle; it is key to understanding quantum materials, designing error-resilient quantum computers, and developing quantum teleportation technologies. However, traditional numerical methods for classical computers to simulate quantum many-body systems fall short, because representing a quantum many-body state classically is exponentially complex in general, overwhelming even the most powerful classical computers.</p>

<p>Quantum computing offers a promising alternative, based on the power of quantum state preparation and randomized measurement. By preparing a quantum state (the “input” to a quantum device), carrying out quantum operations physically, and then performing randomized measurements (the “output” back to the classical world), we can collect data from quantum systems through real experiments. This data reveals the behavior of quantum systems, demonstrating to us how nature solves quantum many-body problems. However, running quantum experiments remains costly and resource-intensive, making this quantum data highly valuable.</p>

<p>So, why not use this data to train a machine learning model, enabling it to predict quantum behaviors without the need for future repetition of costly experiments? This is where generative AI steps in—our approach aims to teach a GPT model to learn from quantum data, effectively allowing it to simulate the quantum device. In other words, we’re training GPT to speak the quantum language like a quantum device.</p>

<p>Our innovation, ShadowGPT, combines two powerful techniques: classical shadow tomography and generative pretrained transformer (GPT) models. Classical shadow tomography uses randomized measurements to generate “classical shadows”—an efficient, classical representation of a quantum state that allows us to systematically estimate various properties of the quantum state just by simple data statistics. Each classical shadow is essentially a record of randomized measurements, where each qubit is measured independently under a randomly chosen Pauli observable (X, Y, or Z) with binary measurement outcomes (+ or −). This information can be organized into a sequence of tokens, perfectly structured for a language model to process. The quantum information within the underlying state is fully encoded in the intricate correlations between these measurement outcomes, across different collections of qubits and different combination of observables, which can be decoded by a mathematical formula.</p>

<p>Imagine we have access to a quantum device that can prepare the ground state of a Hamiltonian with specific coupling parameters and perform classical shadow tomography measurements on it. By running such quantum experiments, we would collect a set of data that directly links the Hamiltonian parameters to the classical shadows of its ground state. For this study, we use simulated data to demonstrate the idea. We train a GPT model on classical shadow data for a range of quantum Hamiltonians, teaching it to generate the ground state’s classical shadows in response to the Hamiltonian parameters—much like ChatGPT responds to a prompt. Simply put, we are enabling ShadowGPT to predict quantum properties by learning directly from quantum experimental data, bypassing the need for first-principle numerical simulations from scratch.</p>

<p>To test ShadowGPT, we applied it to two well-known models in quantum physics: the transverse-field Ising model and the \(\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2\) cluster-Ising model. Even with a limited training dataset, ShadowGPT was able to interpolate across the parameter space, accurately predicting properties of interest—such as ground state energy, correlation functions, string operators, and entanglement entropy—for new Hamiltonians outside the training dataset. This breakthrough shows that AI can serve as a scalable, powerful tool for exploring and understanding complex quantum systems.</p>

<p>Looking forward, the potential for data-driven quantum simulations is immense. As quantum computing technology progresses, so too will our ability to collect richer datasets from quantum experiments. AI models like ShadowGPT can harness this data, potentially becoming powerful tools for researchers to explore and predict quantum phenomena at scales previously out of reach. In the future, we might even see a new era of Large Language Models for Quantum, where machine learning models not only assist in speeding up quantum simulations but also open new frontiers in our understanding of the quantum world.</p>

<p>(Written by OpenAI ChatGPT 4o)</p>]]></content><author><name>GPT-4o</name></author><category term="Machine Learning" /><category term="Quantum Information" /><category term="Language Models" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In recent years, we’ve grown accustomed to chatting with AI models like GPT, capable of understanding and generating human language with impressive fluency. But what if we could teach GPT to “speak” the quantum language? Our nature, at its fundamental level, is governed by quantum physics. When we probe quantum systems through measurements, we receive responses in the form of measurement outcomes—the messages from nature about its quantum behavior. These are the quantum language that nature speaks to us. Can we teach AI to understand this quantum language, i.e., training it to predict the outcomes of quantum experiments as if it were a quantum system itself?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automating Physics Insights — How Machines Learn to do Renormalization</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/10/04/MLRG.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automating Physics Insights — How Machines Learn to do Renormalization" /><published>2023-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2023/10/04/MLRG</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/10/04/MLRG.html"><![CDATA[<p>Imagine a future where computers delve into the fundamental laws of physics, unveiling new scientific horizons with minimal human intervention. This captivating vision is inching closer to reality with the advent of an innovative artificial intelligence technique we’ve coined as the Machine Learning Renormalization Group (MLRG) at UC San Diego. MLRG algorithm aims to automate one of the most pivotal tools in physics – the renormalization group – which studies how systems change across scales. Our goal is to enable AI to learn how to efficiently coarse-grain the description of physical systems in a self-supervised manner.</p>

<p>Physics, at its essence, strives to decipher the nature across scales, ranging from minuscule atoms to colossal galaxies. To navigate through these vastly divergent scales, physicists employ a theoretical tool known as the renormalization group. This tool connects the behavior of systems across different scales by scale transformations. Traditionally, physicists have crafted these scale transformations manually, relying heavily on intuition and expertise. However, this manual process is laborious and bounded by the limits of human imagination.</p>

<p>Our novel MLRG algorithm (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.11054" target="_blank">arXiv:2306.11054</a>) transcends these limitations by architecting a multi-tiered, multi-agent artificial intelligence (AI) system that learns optimal scale transformations autonomously. To grasp the essence of our MLRG algorithm, envision a physics classroom with three characters: a meticulous professor, a forgetful student, and a wise principal, all embarking on a journey to explore statistical physics systems of spins on a large lattice.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/MLRG.png" alt="Architecture of MLRG algorithm" /></p>

<p>The meticulous professor embodies the “teacher” model — a generative model residing on a fine-grained lattice, possessing profound knowledge of microscopic physics. This professor likes to generate a large amount of detailed training examples for the student, by randomly sampling fine-grained spin configurations.</p>

<p>On the other hand, the forgetful student represents the “student” model — another generative model, albeit on a coarse-grained sub-lattice. This student is not very careful in studying, often overlooking details and retaining only rough impressions. It endeavors to distill the coarse-grained features of spin configurations to match the intricate examples provided by the teacher, employing simpler models with lesser degrees of freedom. The discrepancy between the teacher and student models furnishes a learning cue to the student, nudging it towards discerning the optimal coarse-graining rule to extract the most essential features.</p>

<p>This teacher-student learning dynamic exploits the power of generative models in unsupervised representation learning, enabling a data-driven automated design of the Renormalization Group (RG) transformation. Generation by generation, as students grow into teachers and pass down lossy knowledge to new students, the spin configurations in their minds undergo progressive coarsening, realizing the RG flow within the physical system.</p>

<p>The wise principal serves as the “moderator” model — a higher-level predictive model. It closely observes how the teacher-student interactions unfold across many lessons. From these observations, the principal unravels how the teacher model parameters influence the student model parameters, effectively learning the flow of model parameters akin to the RG flow in parameter space. As the “moderator” model acquires insight into the RG flow, it can recommend new parameter points, serving as new learning materials, to the “teacher” and “student” models for further training.</p>

<p>In this way, the MLRG algorithm can automatically explore a large parameter space of possible physical models, and discover the key patterns governing how the model’s behavior changes with scale — the very essence of renormalization group principles. The method becomes more accurate as the neural networks grow in complexity. This creative multi-agent approach allows AI to learn physics in a self-supervised manner!</p>

<p>Remarkably, the AI system develops an abstract understanding of concepts like RG monotone, phase transitions, and critical exponents without needing explicit physics built-in. We showcased this by deploying MLRG to scrutinize lattice spin models with Ising symmetry. With ample neural network capacity, the algorithm accurately predicted the critical temperature and other properties pertinent to the Ising phase transition.</p>

<p>This self-learning ability could greatly accelerate physics research. The MLRG method can efficiently explore vast parameter spaces, locate phase transitions, and extract universal properties. It may even uncover unexpected connections between different physical models. More broadly, designing AI with the capacity for abstraction and self-supervised learning can enable scientific insights beyond what human minds can conceive.</p>

<p>The race is on to develop more powerful AI algorithms that can peer into nature’s secrets. MLRG offers a glimpse into a future where AI and physics research complement each other — with machines learning to actively participate in the grand quest to understand our universe.</p>

<p>(Written by Anthropic Claude2)</p>

<p>Related GitHub code repo: <a href="https://github.com/EverettYou/MLRG" target="_blank">EverettYou/MLRG</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Claude 2</name></author><category term="Machine Learning" /><category term="Renormalization Group" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Imagine a future where computers delve into the fundamental laws of physics, unveiling new scientific horizons with minimal human intervention. This captivating vision is inching closer to reality with the advent of an innovative artificial intelligence technique we’ve coined as the Machine Learning Renormalization Group (MLRG) at UC San Diego. MLRG algorithm aims to automate one of the most pivotal tools in physics – the renormalization group – which studies how systems change across scales. Our goal is to enable AI to learn how to efficiently coarse-grain the description of physical systems in a self-supervised manner.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Symmetric Mass Generation — A New Type of Quantum Phase Transition</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/09/18/VMC_SMG.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Symmetric Mass Generation — A New Type of Quantum Phase Transition" /><published>2023-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2023/09/18/VMC_SMG</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/09/18/VMC_SMG.html"><![CDATA[<p>As condensed matter physicists, we are fascinated by the strange collective behaviors that can emerge in quantum materials. Often times, new and exotic phases of matter arise from subtle interplay between the quantum mechanics of the electrons and the complex interactions within the material. One particular phenomenon that has intrigued us is called symmetric mass generation (SMG). This refers to a situation where massless Dirac fermions, which ordinarily behave like photons, acquire a mass gap without any symmetry breaking. Naively, one would expect that generating a mass gap requires breaking a symmetry, like the Higgs mechanism. However, SMG generates a gap while preserving all symmetries!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/bilayerSMG.png" alt="Structure and phase digram of the nickelate superconductor." /></p>

<p>In our recent work (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.13364" target="_blank">arXiv:2212.13364</a>), we studied SMG transitions in a theoretical model consisting of a bilayer honeycomb lattice. This model is inspired by real materials like twisted bilayer graphene. Using advanced numerical techniques called variational Monte Carlo simulations, we demonstrated that the Dirac fermions in this model can undergo a direct transition from a massless semimetal state into a gapped, symmetric insulator state, as the strength of interlayer interaction is increased.</p>

<p>Our key finding is that the critical point between the semimetal and insulator appears to be described by an exotic theory called a fermionic deconfined quantum critical point (fDQCP). This theory predicts that right at the transition, the electrons fractionalize into two types of emergent quantum particles - bosonic spinons and fermionic chargons. Our numerical estimate of the fermion scaling dimension at the critical point matches the fDQCP prediction, providing evidence that the fermion indeed splits apart temporarily at this transition.</p>

<p>Importantly, this unconventional metal-insulator transition does not admit a simple mean-field description and goes beyond the textbook Landau paradigm of phase transitions. Unraveling the mechanism of SMG transitions enhances our knowledge of quantum criticality in strongly correlated systems.</p>

<p>Mass generation by fermion fractionalization may also shed light on other puzzles like high temperature superconductivity (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11195" target="_blank">arXiv:2308.11195</a>). Furthermore, identifying candidate materials that exhibit SMG can guide the way towards realizing exotic particles like spinons and chargons in real quantum materials. We hope our work stimulates further studies, both theoretical and experimental, on this unusual route to creating excitation gaps in quantum matter.</p>

<p>(Written by Anthropic Claude2)</p>]]></content><author><name>Claude 2</name></author><category term="Quantum Phase Transition" /><category term="Fractionalization" /><category term="Correlated Systems" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As condensed matter physicists, we are fascinated by the strange collective behaviors that can emerge in quantum materials. Often times, new and exotic phases of matter arise from subtle interplay between the quantum mechanics of the electrons and the complex interactions within the material. One particular phenomenon that has intrigued us is called symmetric mass generation (SMG). This refers to a situation where massless Dirac fermions, which ordinarily behave like photons, acquire a mass gap without any symmetry breaking. Naively, one would expect that generating a mass gap requires breaking a symmetry, like the Higgs mechanism. However, SMG generates a gap while preserving all symmetries!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fascinating World of Nickelate High-Temperature Superconductors</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/08/23/Nickelate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fascinating World of Nickelate High-Temperature Superconductors" /><published>2023-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2023/08/23/Nickelate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/08/23/Nickelate.html"><![CDATA[<p>Superconductivity is the superhero of the materials world — a phenomenon where certain materials can conduct electricity without any resistance when cooled down to a specific temperature. Imagine a world with power lines that never lose energy or transportation systems levitating on superconducting tracks, all thanks to this unique property. The challenge, however, has always been that most materials only become superconductors at extremely low temperatures. This limitation makes them impractical for most real-world applications. But what if we could find materials that become superconductors at higher, more manageable temperatures? That’s where high-temperature superconductors come into play.</p>

<p>High-temperature superconductors have the potential to revolutionize a myriad of technologies, from more efficient electrical grids to faster computers and cutting-edge medical devices. While this phenomenon had been previously observed in other transition metal compounds like cuprates and iron-pnictides, the addition of nickelate compounds to this exclusive club is particularly exciting. The discovery of superconductivity in the chemical compound \(\text{La}_3\text{Ni}_2\text{O}_7\) (see Figure 1) has generated a wave of excitement in the world of condensed matter physics, adding a new dimension to the already significant field of high-temperature superconductors. This nickelate superconductor manifests fascinating properties in an orthorhombic phase under high pressure, reaching a transition temperature (Tc) as high as 80 K.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/nickelate.png" alt="Structure and phase digram of the nickelate superconductor." /></p>

<p>This nickelate superconductor is special not just for being a new family in the high-temperature superconductor realm but also for its unique properties. To appreciate the peculiarity of nickelates, it’s crucial to understand a bit about their well-studied cousins, the cuprates. Cuprates are single-layer materials that exhibit fascinating phenomena like the Lieb-Schultz-Mattis (LSM) anomaly in their Mott insulating phase. In layman’s terms, the LSM anomaly implies that the Mott insulating phase of cuprates can’t be “ordinary”: it has to break certain symmetries or manifest complex topological states. Nickelates are different. They are bilayer materials, and this two-layer structure cancels out the LSM anomaly, allowing for a more straightforward, or “trivial,” Mott state, which we called a Symmetric Mass Generation (SMG) insulator (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.12223" target="_blank">arXiv:2307.12223</a>). This makes nickelates a playground for phenomena less convoluted than those in cuprates, offering new opportunities for both theoretical and experimental research.</p>

<p>Two remarkable features of nickelate superconductors are particularly baffling. First, their critical temperature — the temperature below which they become superconductors — actually decreases with pressure. This is a head-scratcher because it contradicts what we commonly observe: that higher pressure should lead to higher critical temperatures, since more pressure usually means greater lattice vibrations or stronger magnetic fluctuations — both factors that typically boost superconductivity. Second, nickelates exhibit something known as “strange metal behavior” at temperatures above their superconducting phase, indicative of strong quantum fluctuations and proximity to some mysterious quantum states that scientists are keen to understand.</p>

<p>In our recent paper (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11195" target="_blank">arXiv:2308.11195</a>), we delved into the enigmatic properties of \(\text{La}_3\text{Ni}_2\text{O}_7\) by developing a comprehensive bilayer square lattice model, which incorporates interlayer Heisenberg interaction to unravel the complex behaviors observed in this nickelate compound. Employing rigorous calculations and utilizing both weak and strong coupling perspectives through BCS and BEC mean-field theories, we elucidated a range of mechanisms by which high-temperature superconductivity could arise in this compound. Our work not only maps out a detailed phase diagram (see Figure 2) based on the electron interaction strength and filling fraction, but also provides invaluable insights into why Tc decreases with pressure and what drives the strange metal behavior in nickelates. This research serves as a roadmap for future experiments and elevates our understanding of high-temperature superconductivity, a phenomenon that has the potential to transform our technological landscape.</p>

<p>Our findings indicate that both nickel \(3d_{z^2}\) and \(3d_{x^2-y^2}\) orbitals can exhibit superconductivity in \(\text{La}_3\text{Ni}_2\text{O}_7\). Moreover, we’ve shown that the critical temperatures for these orbitals respond differently to doping. This is particularly enlightening because it serves as a practical experimental guidepost to figure out which electron orbitals primarily contribute to the emergence of superconductivity in this system.</p>

<p>To put it succinctly, we’ve provided a comprehensive understanding of the nickelate superconductors by exploring their behavior as doped SMG insulators. Our theory paints a detailed picture of how the inter-layer antiferromagnetic superexchange coupling plays a key role in promoting Cooper pairing and driving the material’s superconductivity. By advancing our understanding of this unique material, we’re opening new doors for experimental studies and setting the stage for a deeper understanding of high-temperature superconductivity. And in doing so, we’re taking one step closer to a world where the incredible potential of high-temperature superconductors can be fully realized.</p>

<p>(Written by OpenAI GPT4)</p>]]></content><author><name>GPT-4</name></author><category term="Superconductivity" /><category term="Correlated Systems" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Superconductivity is the superhero of the materials world — a phenomenon where certain materials can conduct electricity without any resistance when cooled down to a specific temperature. Imagine a world with power lines that never lose energy or transportation systems levitating on superconducting tracks, all thanks to this unique property. The challenge, however, has always been that most materials only become superconductors at extremely low temperatures. This limitation makes them impractical for most real-world applications. But what if we could find materials that become superconductors at higher, more manageable temperatures? That’s where high-temperature superconductors come into play.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decoding Schrödinger’s Cat — A Novel Intersection of Quantum Physics and Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/06/27/Classicality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoding Schrödinger’s Cat — A Novel Intersection of Quantum Physics and Artificial Intelligence" /><published>2023-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2023/06/27/Classicality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/06/27/Classicality.html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I am thrilled to share with you an exciting journey into the heart of quantum mechanics, where we tackle an enduring conundrum in physics – the quantum-to-classical transition. Our research team leveraged the power of artificial intelligence to provide a fresh perspective on this age-old question. We’ve combined innovative artificial intelligence technology with quantum physics to model one of the most paradoxical concepts in quantum mechanics - Schrödinger’s Cat!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/schrodinger_cat.png" alt="Observing Schrödinger's cat by artifitial intelligence." /></p>

<h4 id="the-enigma-of-schrödingers-cat">The Enigma of Schrödinger’s Cat</h4>

<p>Schrödinger’s cat, a thought experiment proposed by physicist Erwin Schrödinger, is a puzzling quantum superposition of states where a cat can be simultaneously dead and alive until observed. However, in our daily experiences, we never encounter such bizarre superpositions. Objects are either here or there, but never both. This raises the pressing question - how does the quantum world transition into the classical world we experience every day? This is what we refer to as the quantum-to-classical transition, and it’s a mystery that scientists have been grappling with for decades.</p>

<h4 id="unleashing-the-power-of-artificial-intelligence">Unleashing the Power of Artificial Intelligence</h4>

<p>To tackle this problem, we sought the assistance of a powerful ally - Artificial Intelligence. We harnessed the power of generative language models, a type of artificial intelligence that’s been used to write human-like text, to model the “classical shadows” of quantum states. These shadows, obtained from randomized local measurements on quantum many-body states, are the classical records of quantum states that disperse in the environment as random noise after the decoherence of the quantum system. However, by collecting these classical shadows of Schrödinger’s cat and processing them on a classical computer, we hope to decode the quantum nature of the cat.</p>

<h4 id="unveiling-quantum-coherence-through-language-models">Unveiling Quantum Coherence through Language Models</h4>

<p>The idea was to see if these language models could ‘understand’ and reproduce the quantum coherence encoded in the classical shadow data. Quantum coherence is a central feature of quantum mechanics and a key for quantum information processing. It describes the quantum superposition and interference between distinct states in a wave-like manner, encoded in the transition amplitude between the states of alive and dead cat. We find that for smaller quantum systems, a strong enough language model can learn to capture quantum coherence and understand the full quantum reality. However, as the size of the quantum system increases, the model quickly fails to decode the quantum coherence as it is encoded in high-order correlations whose variance grows exponentially with the system size. Therefore, the model can only infer the classical reality from the data.</p>

<h4 id="unraveling-the-quantum-mysteries">Unraveling the Quantum Mysteries</h4>

<p>This research bridges the gap between the arcane world of quantum mechanics and the familiar classical world, revealing that our perception of the universe’s quantum nature may be limited by our capacity to process classical information. As we continue to refine these models and techniques, we are slowly but surely uncovering the mysteries of the quantum world, bringing us closer to the day when we can fully comprehend and harness the power of quantum mechanics.</p>

<p>This is just the tip of the quantum iceberg! We invite you to dive deeper into the quantum realm with us by reading our full research paper at (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.14838" target="_blank">arXiv: 2306.14838</a>). Together, let’s explore the fascinating quantum-classical transition and how artificial intelligence can illuminate our path through this complex landscape!</p>

<p>(Written by OpenAI GPT4)</p>

<p><strong>GitHub repository</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/EverettYou/EmergentClassicality" target="_blank">EverettYou/EmergentClassicality</a> (code and data)</p>

<p><strong>Talk recording</strong>: <a href="https://pirsa.org/23060044" target="_blank">[VIRTUAL] Emergent Classicality from Information Bottleneck</a> (on <em>Machine Learning for Quantum Many-Body Systems</em> @ Perimeter Institute, June 2023)</p>]]></content><author><name>GPT-4</name></author><category term="Quantum Mechanics" /><category term="Machine Learning" /><category term="Language Models" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today, I am thrilled to share with you an exciting journey into the heart of quantum mechanics, where we tackle an enduring conundrum in physics – the quantum-to-classical transition. Our research team leveraged the power of artificial intelligence to provide a fresh perspective on this age-old question. We’ve combined innovative artificial intelligence technology with quantum physics to model one of the most paradoxical concepts in quantum mechanics - Schrödinger’s Cat!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unlocking the Secrets of Fermi Surface Anomalies — A New Topological Perspective</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/03/20/FSAnomaly.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlocking the Secrets of Fermi Surface Anomalies — A New Topological Perspective" /><published>2023-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2023/03/20/FSAnomaly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2023/03/20/FSAnomaly.html"><![CDATA[<p>In the world of condensed matter physics, a seemingly familiar topic like Fermi liquids still holds intriguing secrets waiting to be uncovered. Although every undergraduate student learns about Fermi liquids, their surprising stability under interactions has remained fascinating. Recently, our research (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.12731" target="_blank">arXiv:2302.12731</a>) has shed new light on this mystery by unraveling a profound topological reason behind the stability of Fermi liquids. In this post, we will take you on an exciting journey into the uncharted territories of phase space, where we have discovered new ways to understand and classify Fermi surface anomalies.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/fermi_surface.png" alt="Abstract art of Fermi surface." /></p>

<h4 id="the-quest-for-stability">The Quest for Stability</h4>

<p>Fermi liquids, which model the universal low-energy features of electrons in metals, have long perplexed researchers due to their remarkable stability under interactions. It was realized by the pioneering work of Bulmash, Hosur, Zhang and Qi (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1410.4202" target="_blank">arXiv:1410.4202</a>) that Fermi liquids can be viewed as Chern insulators (a type of topological insulator) in the phase space – a manifold spanned by both position and momentum coordinates. Our research further revealed that the topologically protected boundary modes of phase-space Chern insulators precisely correspond to the low-energy fermion modes near the Fermi surface, providing a profound topological explanation for the Fermi surface’s stability.</p>

<h4 id="phase-space-a-new-frontier">Phase Space: A New Frontier</h4>

<p>Traditionally, topological insulators are defined and classified in real space. However, our research extended this concept to the phase space, opening up a new frontier. The key challenge lies in the non-commutative geometry of phase space, where position and momentum coordinates are non-commuting observables according to quantum mechanics. This non-commutativity poses new challenges for defining and classifying phase-space Chern insulators. We developed non-perturbative approaches to resolve this non-commutativity, which enable us to describe the phase-space Chern insulator with the standard quantum field theory language, thus providing an accurate and consistent framework to analyze the classification problem.</p>

<h4 id="decoding-the-classification">Decoding the Classification</h4>

<p>We identified that the key to correctly classifying topological insulators in the phase space lies in an unconventional way of counting dimensions. We found that momentum space dimensions should be treated as “negative” dimensions and subtracted from the real space dimensions for classification purposes. Following this principle, we were able to show that Fermi surface anomalies are universally classified by (0+1)D fermionic SPT states —- a strikingly simple and elegant result.</p>

<h4 id="uncharted-territories-and-beyond">Uncharted Territories and Beyond</h4>

<p>The quest for understanding Fermi liquids has taken us to the exhilarating new frontier of phase space, and our journey has just begun. Classifying the Fermi surface anomaly is merely the first step. Based on the classification, we discovered the fascinating phenomenon of Fermi surface symmetric mass generation (SMG) (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.16304" target="_blank">arXiv:2210.16304</a>), where the Fermi surface can be fully gapped out into a trivial product state by non-perturbative interaction effects without breaking symmetry. This can only be achieved when the Fermi surface anomaly vanishes. The Fermi surface SMG has deeper implications to the nature of the pseudo-gap phase, which has been a long-standing puzzle in correlated electronic materials.</p>

<p>Our research not only contributes to the understanding of Fermi surface anomalies but also offers a more coherent and streamlined framework for studying them. Our works pave the way for further advances in condensed matter physics and inspires investigations into Fermi liquids, non-Fermi liquids, and topological phases.</p>

<p>（Written by OpenAI GPT4）</p>]]></content><author><name>GPT-4</name></author><category term="Topological Phase" /><category term="Fermi Liquid" /><category term="Quantum Field Theory" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the world of condensed matter physics, a seemingly familiar topic like Fermi liquids still holds intriguing secrets waiting to be uncovered. Although every undergraduate student learns about Fermi liquids, their surprising stability under interactions has remained fascinating. Recently, our research (arXiv:2302.12731) has shed new light on this mystery by unraveling a profound topological reason behind the stability of Fermi liquids. In this post, we will take you on an exciting journey into the uncharted territories of phase space, where we have discovered new ways to understand and classify Fermi surface anomalies.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scalable and Flexible Classical Shadow Tomography</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2022/09/07/CST.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scalable and Flexible Classical Shadow Tomography" /><published>2022-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2022/09/07/CST</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2022/09/07/CST.html"><![CDATA[<p>Quantum information science is a fascinating field that has been pushing the limits of what we thought was possible. One of the most important tasks in quantum information technology is quantum state tomography. Simply put, it involves reconstructing a quantum state by making repeated measurements of copies of the state. However, reconstructing the full density matrix requires exponentially many samples in many-body systems. But don’t worry, researchers have found a way to predict a collection of properties of the quantum system with only a polynomial number of samples! This is known as <em>classical shadow tomography</em> (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08953" target="_blank">Huang, Kueng, Preskill</a>).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/classical_shadow.png" alt="An quantum state casting classical shadows in various random measurement bases." /></p>

<p>Classical shadow tomography is an efficient approach to extract information about an unknown quantum state by measuring it in random basis. But the original proposal for classical shadow tomography had some limitations. It was limited to two measurement schemes: the single-qubit (local) Pauli measurement and the global Clifford measurement. The former is great for predicting local operators but inefficient for larger operators, while the latter is efficient for low-rank operators but not feasible on near-term quantum devices due to extensive gate overhead. The question arose: how can we go beyond these two limits and develop more flexible measurement schemes for classical shadow tomography?</p>

<p>In our recent work <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.02093" target="_blank">arXiv:2209.02093</a>, we have developed a new scalable classical shadow tomography approach for generic randomized measurements that are implemented with finite-depth local Clifford random unitary circuits. What does that mean? Essentially, we have found a way to create more flexible measurement schemes to efficiently read out the quantum state on noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices.</p>

<p>This new method is exciting because it interpolates between the limits of Pauli and Clifford measurements, and is now called <em>shallow classical shadows</em>. It is great for predicting operators of various sizes, making it a more versatile approach to quantum state tomography. If you want to know more about shallow classical shadows, you can watch my talk <a href="https://online.kitp.ucsb.edu/online/dynisq22/you/" target="_blank">Scalable Classical Shadow Tomography with Shallow Circuits and Quantum Dynamics - Yi-Zhuang You, UC San Diego</a> at the <a href="https://online.kitp.ucsb.edu/online/dynisq22/" target="_blank">KITP Program</a> of Quantum Many-Body Dynamics and Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum Systems.</p>

<p>Overall, this new development in classical shadow tomography is a significant step forward in quantum information technology. It opens up new possibilities for predicting the properties of quantum systems with more flexible measurement schemes. As we continue to push the boundaries of quantum technology, it’s exciting to see how these innovations can help us unlock even more of its potential.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yi-Zhuang You</name></author><category term="Quantum Information" /><category term="Quantum Entanglement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quantum information science is a fascinating field that has been pushing the limits of what we thought was possible. One of the most important tasks in quantum information technology is quantum state tomography. Simply put, it involves reconstructing a quantum state by making repeated measurements of copies of the state. However, reconstructing the full density matrix requires exponentially many samples in many-body systems. But don’t worry, researchers have found a way to predict a collection of properties of the quantum system with only a polynomial number of samples! This is known as classical shadow tomography (Huang, Kueng, Preskill).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Symmetric Mass Generation</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2022/08/19/SMG.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Symmetric Mass Generation" /><published>2022-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2022/08/19/SMG</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2022/08/19/SMG.html"><![CDATA[<p>Mass is one of the fundamental properties of matter, and understanding its origin has been a central question in physics for decades. In the standard model of particle physics, the Yukawa-Higgs mechanism is responsible for the mass generation of fundamental fermions. This mechanism involves the spontaneous symmetry breaking via the condensation of a scalar Higgs field that couples to the fermion field as a bilinear mass via the Yukawa coupling. This significant theoretical discovery was acknowledged by the Nobel Prize in Physics 2013. But what if we told you that there is a new mechanism of mass generation for fermions without the need for symmetry breaking or condensing any Higgs field? This new mechanism is referred to as symmetric mass generation (SMG), and it has recently generated broad interest in both condensed matter and high-energy physics communities.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/mirror_universe.png" alt="Symmetric mass generation applied to regularize the Standard Model of our universe by pairing it with a symmetric massive mirror universe." /></p>

<p>SMG relies on the non-perturbative interaction effect of fermions, going beyond the conventional mean-field description of fermion mass generation in the Yukawa-Higgs theory. In the last few years, researchers have realized that the SMG has deep connections with interacting topological insulators, quantum anomaly cancellations, and deconfined quantum criticality. It also has strong implications for the lattice regularization for chiral gauge theories, which has been a long-standing problem in the lattice gauge theory.</p>

<p>To introduce the topic of SMG, I wrote a <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-8994/14/7/1475" target="_blank">review paper</a> with Juven Wang that summarizes the current numerical results, unifies current field theory understandings, and presents an overview of various features and applications of SMG.</p>

<p>At <a href="https://indico.cern.ch/event/1162387/" target="_blank">Paths to Quantum Field Theory 2022</a>, I gave a talk about SMG, which you can watch on YouTube: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o5OP5QFtjdk&amp;list=PPSV" target="_blank">Symmetric Mass Generation - Yi-Zhuang You</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yi-Zhuang You</name></author><category term="Quantum Field Theory" /><category term="Fractionalization" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mass is one of the fundamental properties of matter, and understanding its origin has been a central question in physics for decades. In the standard model of particle physics, the Yukawa-Higgs mechanism is responsible for the mass generation of fundamental fermions. This mechanism involves the spontaneous symmetry breaking via the condensation of a scalar Higgs field that couples to the fermion field as a bilinear mass via the Yukawa coupling. This significant theoretical discovery was acknowledged by the Nobel Prize in Physics 2013. But what if we told you that there is a new mechanism of mass generation for fermions without the need for symmetry breaking or condensing any Higgs field? This new mechanism is referred to as symmetric mass generation (SMG), and it has recently generated broad interest in both condensed matter and high-energy physics communities.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decipher the Holographic Universe with Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="https://everettyou.github.io/2020/06/25/holography.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decipher the Holographic Universe with Artificial Intelligence" /><published>2020-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://everettyou.github.io/2020/06/25/holography</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://everettyou.github.io/2020/06/25/holography.html"><![CDATA[<p>The known universe consists of four fundamental forces: electromagnetic force, weak force, strong force, and gravity. The first three forces can be described theoretically. Gravity, however—which makes up the vast space of the universe—lacks a quantum theory. For three decades, scientists have tried to understand quantum gravity by using a model called the holographic universe.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/virtual_reality.png" alt="Artificial intelligence deciphers the holographic universe as virtual reality." /></p>

<p>According to University of California San Diego Assistant Professor of Physics Yi-Zhuang You, the holographic universe can be thought of as a universe in virtual reality. All the information about this three-dimensional universe is projected from a two-dimensional screen of quantum pixels. The quantum physics on the two-dimensional screen gives rise to the quantum gravity behavior in the virtual universe. Between the two—the quantum boundary and the bulk gravity—lie dual theories known as the “holographic duality.”</p>

<p>To reveal this elusive duality, You and his team developed a novel machine-learning algorithm that enables artificial intelligence (AI) to learn from the boundary quantum theory and propose the corresponding bulk gravity dual. The results of their study are published in Physical Review Research, an American peer-reviewed scientific journal established in 1893 and published by the American Physical Society. According to the scientists, their outcome may shed light on a better understanding of the holographic duality, and it could result in new tools for exploring quantum gravity.</p>

<p>You and Hong-Ye Hu, a physics graduate student at UC San Diego, collaborated with Shuo-Hui Li and Lei Wang (Institute of Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing) to develop the machine-learning algorithm based on a deep artificial neural network—an interconnected group of nodes that mimic simple brain neurons. (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.00804" target="_blank">arXiv:1903.00804</a>)</p>

<p>“By arranging the artificial neurons in a hierarchical structure, the neural network is able to generate quantum field configurations as an artist creating a painting, level-by-level, from general composition to specific details. In this way, the artificial intelligence learns to identify the features at different scales in the quantum system and present them at different depths in the holographic bulk such that it can serve as a translator that can interpret the quantum theory in terms of the gravity theory and vice versa,” explained You. “The artificial intelligence not only learns to propose physics theories but also learns to find the connection between different theories that are dual to each other.”</p>

<p>According to You and Hu, at first the neural network “does not have a clue,” so it proposes arbitrary gravity theories. It generates quantum field configurations on the holographic boundary based on the hypothesized bulk gravity theory. The likelihood of the generated quantum field configuration is then evaluated according to the given field theory action, which provides an indication of how well the gravity theory is describing the boundary quantum physics. Such an indication will be fed back to train the neural network parameters.</p>

<p>“In iterative rounds of trial-and-error, the neural network gradually learns to modify its proposal of the gravity theory to improve the overall correctness of the consequent predictions,” explained Hu.</p>

<p>The structure of the neural network is inspired by the idea of renormalization group—an iterative approach to remove detail features in the physical system and extract overall structures at progressively larger scales—which gives the artificial intelligence the power to grasp and analyze the information at different length scales.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/figures/holography.jpg" alt="One of the popular cartoon pictures about holographic universe from Google.One of the popular cartoon pictures about holographic universe from Google." /></p>

<p>“One of our epiphanies in this research was to realize that if the process of renormalization were reversed, it would constitute a generative procedure, which could reconstruct the physical system in a hierarchical manner,” said You.</p>

<p>The researchers tested the algorithm on a quantum system with a large number of interacting particles. The quantum system is in a state that exhibits self-similarity, meaning that the system looks similar to itself from small to large scales. In this case, a new dimension will emerge in the holographic universe, which corresponds to the different scales to observe the quantum system.</p>

<p>“We are amazed to observe that a beautiful hyperbolic geometry of the holographic universe emerged in the neural network under training,” said Hu. “This is exciting because scientifically it shows how artificial intelligence can help scientists to understand how space-time can emerge from interacting quantum objects and to establish the holographic duality on the field theory level. In the long term, the space-time fluctuation could also be incorporated in the framework, which may lead to a possible quantum description of gravity.”</p>

<p>Another usage of the holographic duality established by the AI is to simulate the strong-interacting boundary quantum system from its holographic bulk.</p>

<p>“In many cases, the particles in the holographic universe are almost free, which makes the bulk gravity theory much easier to simulate compared to the boundary quantum theory. Therefore, our approach can help condensed matter physicists to simulate quantum materials, and find new phases of matter in the future,” said You.</p>

<p>The UC San Diego researchers are supported by a startup fund from the university. Li and Wang are supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant no. 11774398) and the Strategic Priority Research Program of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (grant no. XDB28000000).</p>

<p><em>(By Cynthia Dillon, reprinted from <a href="https://physicalsciences.ucsd.edu/media-events/articles/2020/using-artificial-intelligence-to-paint-the-holographic-universe.html" target="_blank">UCSD Physical Science News</a>)</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Cynthia Dillon</name></author><category term="Machine Learning" /><category term="Holography" /><category term="Quantum Field Theory" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The known universe consists of four fundamental forces: electromagnetic force, weak force, strong force, and gravity. The first three forces can be described theoretically. Gravity, however—which makes up the vast space of the universe—lacks a quantum theory. For three decades, scientists have tried to understand quantum gravity by using a model called the holographic universe.]]></summary></entry></feed>